<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Rakesh Kasibhatla</title>
 <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io"/>
 <updated>2023-10-29T16:48:59+05:30</updated>
 <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Rakesh Kasibhatla</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>USA Trip 2023 - Reflections - Part 5</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2023/10/29/us-trip-reflections-p5/"/>
   <updated>2023-10-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2023/10/29/us-trip-reflections-p5</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We wanted to keep the next day a bit light and also my friend had to go to his office for some work. So after a quick breakfast, I met my former colleague for coffee. It was great to see him, and he was the last one on my checklist of friends to meet in the US. It’s always great to meet your friend after a long time and have a good chat. Next, I headed off to the Google office where my friend was working and had a relaxing massage in one of the famous massage chairs at Google. We also had a great lunch at the Google cafeteria and I got to experience the famed gourmet Google food. After lunch, I spent the rest of the day at my friends home just lazing around and watching a movie in Netflix. I got to experience the connected home tech with Google Home at his apartment, and it was magical. That evening, I headed out to meet my cousin for dinner and after a fulfilling south Indian dinner, I headed to my cousin’s home for the rest of my stay in the US. Wishing your friends good bye is always painful and it was no different for me when I had to bid farewell to my friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, we refreshed and headed out to a neighborhood mall and shopped some more. After a delicious lunch prepared by my cousins’ wife, we started our way back to home – India. The drive to airport was again special – we drove through places that hosted our office and the hotel. Looking at them, I was reminded of my time in the US – what a beautiful 2 week journey it was! Finally, we reached the airport and finished all the formalities. As I sat the boarding gate waiting for my flight boarding, I saw something dearest to me – the Indian flag on my plane. I was never more happy seeing my country flag. As the plane took off, I bid farewell to US – the land that gave me so many memories over the past 2 weeks and I signed off until the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I take away from this trip? A lot of memories, some captured here some captured in my heart. This trip was special to me on more than one front – professionally and personally. Looking back, I realized that life has a perfect timing for everything for us. After a tumultuous 6 months, life rewarded me with beautiful 2 weeks of relaxation and rejuvenation – both for my body and my soul. A friend of mine always used to say – believe in the timing of God and manifestation. This US trip of mine made me realize those words and I am thankful to the God for bestowing me this memorable trip.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Factfulness by Hans Rosling</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2023/08/01/factfulness/"/>
   <updated>2023-08-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2023/08/01/factfulness</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with a question -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘There are 2 billion children in the world today, aged 0 to 15 years old. How many children will there be in the year 2100, according to the United Nations?’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A: 4 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;B: 3 billion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C: 2 billion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to search for an answer on the internet, take your best guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The correct answer is C. Did that surprise you? You were probably thinking along the lines of 4 billion or more, given what we currently know about the population growth in the world today. Well, you are not alone. It turns out that some of the best minds in the Governments, media, public health also are in the same boat. We are no better than chimpanzees selecting the answers(it sounds harsh, but it’s a statistical fact).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question posed above is just one of the many such questions that are answered in this amazing book - Factfulness. Now, it’s not a book on just some world facts presented as quiz preparatory material. The real intention of Hans Rosling is to change the perception of the world that we carry with us all the time using real statistics from trusted sourcs such as UNO, UNICEF, The World Bank, etc. But why does he care? Or rather, why should we care about these facts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, without the factual data, we have a very distorted view of the world around us. We often think in terms of ‘developed’ and ‘developing’ nations, ‘rich’ and ‘poor’ and many such dichotomies. In reality, it’s a very different scenario out there. Why does this matter? It matters to the leaders of the world to make better decisions in terms of spending public money. It matters to the business heads to invest their resources in better markets - where they can impact peoples lives and make money. It matters to us, as the citizens of the world to understand our own world better. So, how does Hans do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginnning of this book, Hans Rosling presents us with 13 such questions with answers. He then takes each one of these questions and provides the rationale behind why we end up choosing the wrong answer using 10 human insincts that we all have. Instincts such as ‘The Gap Instinct’, ‘The Negativity Instinct’, ‘The Fear Instinct’, ‘The Generalization Instinct’ and so on. I have never come across a more delightful amalgamation of psychology, economics, statistics and inferences so far. As you read through each chapter, you will be surprised to realize how deeply ingrained those insincts are in our minds that lead us to such wrong perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With deeply personal stories about public healthcare in the poorest of the nations of the world, Hans Rosling takes us through the lives of extremely under privileged and needy people that are heart touching and are bound to move us to the core. If you are reading this review, you are already in Level 4(read this book to understand the levels) and there are billions of people still on Levels 2 and 3. And it takes books like these to atleast change the way we think about our people, systems and ideologies. I’m sure after reading this book, your perception of the world will change forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact - you will find a lot of unfinished houses in the city of Tunisia and people still live in them. Can you guess why? The answer will baffle you! But wait, you will have to read this book to find out!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Creative Confidence by Tom Kelly and David Kelly</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/08/10/creative-confidence/"/>
   <updated>2022-08-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/08/10/creative-confidence</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When you hear the word “creativity”, what do you think of next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first line in the book ‘Creative Confidence’ by Tom Kelly and David Kelly. Take a moment and think about that question. If the words that come to your mind are along the lines of ‘drawing’, ‘art’ and ‘music’, you’re not alone. Nine out of ten times, we often conjure up the images of an artist or a painter toiling away at his/her desk ‘creating’ the next masterpiece. We rarely think of creativity in terms of it’s real dictionary meaning - the use of imagination or original ideas to create something - on in other words, ‘inventiveness’. ‘Create something’ is the key here, and it’s not limited to just the discipline of art. This is the first fundamental concept that the authors clarify in this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, why this book? David Kelly is the founder of the IDEO company which is excels at designing products and solutions to companies worldwide. Fun fact - IDEO designed the first manufacturable computer mouse for Apple, and one of its founders pioneered interaction design. So when I came across this book, it was surely tempting enough. And with all the drive around innovation and creativity everywhere, this book fits perfectly as the 101 book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often hear about how competetive the world is becoming and how everyone - companies and individuals alike - need to be more creative or innovative to stay ahead of the curve. While this urgency to get creative is good, what is not articulated is how we reach there. It’s not rare to hear someone in the management asking its employees to be more creative at some all-hands meet. Or organize an yearly ‘hackathon’ event, full of freebies. But this book shows us that it doesn’t need to happen once in a year or in a quarter. Through the chapters, the authors provide very clear and practical steps to get creative, in a tone that sounds more like a friend than an instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A central idea in the book is the emphasis on ‘doing something’. It sounds very simple, but as the authors explain, this is the fundamental hindrance to start getting creative. We often have ideas, but simply lack the effort or courage to take the first step. A best example is my desire to get better at ‘writing’ - I have read multiple books on writing and grammar including ‘On Writing Well’, ‘Elements of Style’ - but it’s only when I actually started writing what you’re reading now that I started noticing changes in my writing. And I am not writing fiction or giving my perspective on a subject after deep research; it’s just writing about something I’ve read. Just this simple activity helped me explore my creative side in writing - how do I start? how does the flow go? where do I stop? how do I spark interest in the readers? Trust me, all we need is the first step! With the ideas presented in this book, I’m sure everyone can start taking that first step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’re some interesting lines from the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doubts in one’s creative ability can be cured by guiding people through a series of small successes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fear of failure is the single biggest obstacle people face to creative success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want more success, you have to be prepared to shrug off more failure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Success has many fathers, but failure is an orphan. To learn from failure, however, you have to ‘own’ it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Do the thing you fear, and the death of fear is certain” - R.W.Emerson.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Courage is only the accumulation of small steps” - Gyorgy Konrad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“If you want a good idea, start with a lot of ideas” - Linus Pauling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“It’s not what you don’t know that gets you into trouble, it’s what you know for sure that ain’t so” - Mark Twain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focusing our energy on the right question can make the difference between incremental improvement and breakthrough innovation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Do or do not. There is no try.” - Yoda in Star Wars.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The desire to be best can get in the way of getting better.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The front end of innovation is supposed to be messy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never go to a meeting without a prototype.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passion doesn’t preclude effort.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leaders can’t dictate culture, but they can nurture it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read, write, create, do something!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Build by Tony Fadell</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/07/27/build/"/>
   <updated>2022-07-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/07/27/build</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I distinctly remember that day. It was 2005 and my friend had got a shiny new gadget from the USA. It was…different. Unlike anything I saw earlier. It had a shiny stainless steel case, a polished white front and a large wheel in the center. Up until then, I had seen physical buttons being arranged in a circular shape, but this wheel was different. It was a touch panel! As I operated it with curiosity, I realized one thing - I was blown away by the experience of using a ‘click-wheel’. You could make circular gestures on that wheel and it would translate them into navigation actions in the software. It’s taking a 2-D motion and mapping onto 1-D actions. Pretty cool! By this time, I’m sure you would’ve guessed the device I have been talking about - the iPod. It was heavy, little big for the pocket at that time, but it was magic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read somewhere about a new book written by Tony Fadell, the creator of iPod, I knew I had to read it. And that’s how this review was born. Tony Fadell needs no introduction if you follow the trends in the tech industry. Even if you missed on his latest creation - Nest Learning Thermostat - you couldn’t have missed iPod or iPhone. Now, when a guy with that kind of background writes a book about advice, you’d expect it to be good. Well, this book is great! In fact, if there’s one book that you should have on your work desk, this can be the one. Why? Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build is a book on advice at work. But it’s not one of those business books that explain some theory followed by some case studies and then followed by an action plan. Build falls somewhere between a memoir and a business book, providing raw and honest advice drawn from the experiences of Tony Fadell over his career span of almost 30 years in Silicon Valley. This is the advice you get when you talk to someone who you are really close with and who has seen a lot of action in his/her career. But not all of us are lucky enough to get to interact with such people. Luckily, for us, Build is one such book. It’s got all the advice you can ever get, at whatever stage of your career you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you read through this book, you will realize that it takes you on a journey of someone starting right out of college, finding the first job, working hard at that job with your heroes, quitting that job, starting your own company, get acquired by a large company, and then creating the best products, quit again, start another company, getting acquired by another large company, and then quit again to help others starting new ventures. Yes, this is one heck of a lifetime journey, and that’s exactly what makes this book the go-to reference in your career. There’s advice about picking the right company to work for, starting a team and building a team culture, delivering a world-class product, talking to customers, hiring your first employees, dealing with law suits and lawyers and much, much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you finish reading this book, I’m sure you’ll come out a bit different than before - one who realizes the importance of every little detail of the work, why work really matters, why do people matter. And that’s a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some interesting lines from the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A good mentor won’t hand you the answers, but they will try to help you see your problem from a new perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adulthood is your opportuinty to screw up continually until you learn how to screw up a little bit less.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask for forgiveness, not permission.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making a mistake is the best way to not make that mistake again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do, fail, learn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re not solving a real problem, you can’t start a revolution.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow your curiosity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any job working with your heroes is a good job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone under you does something spectacular, that just shows the company that you’ve built a great team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The amount of energy needed to refute bullshit is an order of magnitude higher than to produce it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People won’t remember how you started. They’ll remember how you left.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can’t just hit customers on the head with the ‘what’ before you tell them the ‘why’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A good story is an act of empathy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The only way to move forward is to do an honest accounting of the past.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best ideas are painkillers, not vitamins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What you’re building never matters as much as who you’re building it with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best marketing is just telling the truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just some of the lines from the book. There are entire paragraphs worth printing and distributing as flash cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy reading. And learning.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Never Split The Difference by Chris Voss</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/07/09/never-split/"/>
   <updated>2022-07-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/07/09/never-split</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve all been there - the crucial few minutes of our life when we’re trying to get what’s right for us while discussing the possible options with a counterpart. We go back and forth, re-calculate, reconsider, re-evaluate - all to get the best possible deal. Be it at a grocery store or a job interview or a high stake merger/acquisition deal, all we want is to extract the best value proposition. What we are doing in all these situations is ‘negotiation’. Now, everytime we hear the word negotiation, we natually conjure up the images of a top cop trying to talk to a terrorist or captor in a high adrenaline backdrop. What we often miss is the omnipresence of this communication pattern in our daily life and eventually fail to achieve the best outcome of a deal. In a way, it makes sense - how do we get better at something we don’t even realize is happening with us all the time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Never Split The Difference’ by Chris Voss is a book that tries to fill the exact communication skill gap which is very important yet is often not taught at school. True to the scene that I mentioned earlier, this book contains real life stories of hostage situations - all high voltage and extremely gripping - to drive a key lesson in negotiation. Chris Voss, a former FBI hostage negotiator, takes us through the intricacies of a hostage situation in every chapter and from that situation he makes a strong lesson on the art of negotiation. Over the course of the book, Chris Voss demonstrates that it’s empathy and treating the counterpart with respect that goes a long way to make a successful deal - the one in which both the parties are satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this book falls into the genre of communication, it does not delve into the theory of general communication. Instead, what it does - through nerve gripping real life stories - is teach invaluable lessons necessary to successfully get our message through to the counterpart and receive the desired favor in return. In just 10 chapters, Chris Voss takes us through every possible scenario in our lives which require some subtle skill of negotation - be it salary negotiation, or getting a marketing deal from a high profile company, bargaining the rent of a house, getting a seat on an already booked flight, or sending an email that never gets ignored and many more. And it’s not just one or two broad principles that he applies, it’s a whole ammunition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many of us usually think of negotiation as a means of getting things our way at the cost of others, I’m sure that opinion will definitely change once you read this book. In the end, negotiation is all about overcoming the situation, not the adversary.It’s about uncovering the value, an empathic search for the best possible deal and not to strong-arm or humiliate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the very interesting lines from the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People want to be understood and accepted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You get what you ask for; you just have to ask correctly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We fear what’s different and are drawn to what’s similar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘No’ is the &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; of the negotiation, not the &lt;em&gt;end&lt;/em&gt; of it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creative solutions are almost always preceded by some degree of risk, annoyance, confusion and conflict.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your reputation precedes you. Let it precede you in a way that paves success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The chance for loss incites more risk than the possiblity of equal gain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hope is not a strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All negotiation is an information-gathering process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Yes’ is nothing without ‘how’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never be needy for a deal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The person across the table is never the problem. The unsolved issue is. So focus on the issue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the pressure is on, you don’t rise to the occassion; you fall to your highest level of preparation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Listen, listen again and listen some more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Range by David Epstein</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/05/21/range/"/>
   <updated>2022-05-21T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/05/21/range</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lets’s start with a quick observation task: the next time you visit a big hospital, take a close look at the name plates of the doctors offering their services at the hospital. In particular, pay close attention to the areas of medicine they specialize. It’s not surprising at all if you can’t really make sense of some of the specializations - don’t blame yourself. However, you can partly pass on the blame to ‘specialization’. We live in a hyper-specialized world today, whether it’s medicine, engineering, music or sport. We celebrate experts and expertise more than ever today and we often quote them as inspirational model to the younger generation. What makes them special?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the crucial factors to achieve expertise is the concept of head start - which is basically starting very early in one chosen area of skill. Perhaps sport and music provide the most commonly encountered examples for this head start. The stories of Tiger Woods and Serena Williams are the best examples of this phenomenon. Another famous rule contributing to expertise that has been doing rounds in the pop culture is the 10,000 hour rule - deliberate practice for atleast 10,000 hours in a given skill to gain mastery. But, does it have to be this way to be successful in life? ‘Range’ attempts to take a different route which at first seems quite contrary - ‘generalism’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this day and age of specialization, David Epstein takes an unconventional topic that’s the exact opposite of it. In ‘Range’, David Epstein takes us through the lives and worlds of wildly successful masters who were actually generalists - either in the early part of their life or through out - and presents a very refreshing perspective of success. You will come across achievers such as Roger Federer, Vincent Van Gogh, Kepler who have been generalists more than specialists of a particular area. Besides the people, David Epstein also takes us through history in Italy, crucial decision making scenes in NASA, amazingly innovative labs of 3M company, evolution of Nintendo as a gaming company and much more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fundamental concept that ‘Range’ lays is ‘kind world’ vs ‘wicked world’. Now, the terms have got nothing to do with the human behavioral aspects. Rather, they’re the conceptualization of the way world presents itself to us in our daily life. David Epstein makes a very clever distinction between these worlds and he very interestingly differentiates the skillsets that thrive in each of the worlds. True to the theme of the book, he brings home the point of understanding the current world that we are operating and provides essential advice to becoming sucessful in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’re some interesting words from the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The more a task shifts to an open world of big-picture strategy, the more humans have to add.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone needs habits of mind that allow them to dance across disciplines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creativity may be difficult to nurture, but it is easy to thwart.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Struggling to generate an answer on your own, even a wrong one, enhances subsequent learning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning deeply means learning slowly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exploration is not just a whimsical luxury of education; it is a central benefit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A mind kept wide open will take something from every new experience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We learn who we are in practice, not in theory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be careful not to be too careful, or you will unconsciously limit your exploration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compare yourself to yourself yesterday, not to younger people who aren’t you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t feel behind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Invention - A Life by James Dyson</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/04/15/james-dyson/"/>
   <updated>2022-04-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/04/15/james-dyson</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There is a famous quote by Thomas Edison when he invented the electric bulb that goes something like this - “I have not failed. I’ve just found 10,000 ways that won’t work.” 10000 attempts is surely a big number and it certainly seems like a very rare feat. The first line that you read in ‘Invention: A life’ - an autobiography by Sir James Dyson - proves that the huge number of attempts to invent something is not all that rare. To be precise, Sir Dyson made 5,217 prototypes of vacuum cleaners over a period of 4 years in his equivalent of a ‘garage’ before he could build the final version. Do you really need to build 5,217 prototypes for a vacuum cleaner? May be not, but that’s something you will discover as you read the pages further about his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why pick up a book on James Dyson? Well, I was first introduced to Dyson when I came across their bladeless fans and that kind of overturned my understanding of air flow until then. Later, I used a Dyson hand dryer and was once again surprised at the efficiency of the machine(it dries up the hand completely in 10 seconds without any heat). And then I came across the cordless vacuum cleaner that was the most aesthetically designed vacuum cleaner ever(who thought vacuum cleaners can be sexy!) That’s it! I was hooked on to this company and naturally it’s founder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dyson is a British family owned company that has revolutionized certain home appliances such as vacuum cleaners, air purifiers(bladeless, if you remember), hand dryers, hair dryers, hair stylers, and much more. Their most recent innovation is a noise canceling headphones that has built in air-purifier that doubles as a face mask. In many ways, as you will discover, Dyson is very similar to Apple - whether it’s the standards of quality, drive for perfection, beautiful and elegant design, simplicity of use and relentless innovation. In fact, Sir Dyson has an interesting event in life similar to Steve Jobs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From early on in his life, Sir Dyson realizes the importance of design in the area of manufacturing and how it cannot be seen separately. He stresses the need for engineers to include design thinking in every invention and every product they make. He believes that design is something that cannot be done as a decorative aspect of any product. In fact, he actually like to expose the underlying pieces of his invention boldly(his vacuum cleaners have transparent body). This kind of thinking comes from his experience at Royal College of Art(RCA) and from his mentors Jeremy Fry, Tony, etc. This is an invaluable lesson for any engineer because most of the time we are focused on solving the problem alone rather than design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the book, you will read about his various inventions - starting from re-imagining a wheel barrow to building a cyclone vacuum cleaner, a sea truck, a washing machine, a garden water feature(the water appears to flow in reverse in this structure), a board room table with no legs, a contraption for a fashion show, an early precursor to Google Glass, air multipliers, air purifiers, hair dryers, hair stylers, robotic vacuum cleaners and even an electric car! Not all of these inventions have been commercially successful but they give an insight into the genius he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life, as it should be, was not always pleasant for Sir James Dyson. In fact, he was in debt for most of his adult life - even with a family of 3 small kids. It’s just impossible to imagine the kind of perseverance and grit this man has during the tough times. And it’s not just one time, but multiple times - sometimes it was the politics and government, sometimes it was companies stealing his inventions, other times the patent law. I can’t think of a better example for the quote - “If it doesn’t kill you, it will make you stronger” and stronger he became through his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from his inventions, you will also read about his contributions to the areas of farming, education, philanthropy etc. It is his quest to build better engineering talent in UK and the world that led him to establish his own university and provide grants to multiple universities across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some quotes from the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visceral experience is a powerful teacher.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experience tells you what you ought to do and what you’d do best to avoid. It tells you how things should be done when we are much more interested in how things &lt;em&gt;should’t&lt;/em&gt; be done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is easier and safer to take a big risk with a product if it is one that you would use yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow your own star.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Permanently dissatisfied is how an engineer should feel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scale comes with both increasing possibilities and responsibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Education should be about problem solving rather than retaining knowledge simply to pass exams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design is about expressing the engineering or technology inside the product, not styling or about trying to be contemporary for the sake of it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is no greater danger than satisfaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By its very nature, pioneering will not always be successful, otherwise it would be all too easy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Atomic Habits by James Clear</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/03/19/atomic-habits/"/>
   <updated>2022-03-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2022/03/19/atomic-habits</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let me start with a quick introspection: How many times have you thought of picking up a new skill? or perhaps achieving a goal? or maybe lose/gain weight? I bet we all have such desires and we do put in a lot of effort to achieve them. We start with resolutions on every new year eve and start working towards them with a lot of zeal. But then, slowly, something unexpected happens. We start deviating from our new commitments and we often end up quitting sometime mid-journey. Why does this happen? How can we stick to our goals? Through motivation? hardwork? perseverance? focus? Although all of the above factors are necessary, there’s still some missing magic that can help us become successful in our endeavors. Atomic Habits is a book that explores that magic - habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atomic Habits is not just another book on the subject of habit formation or the psychology behind that. This is more of a handbook, or a work-guide on how to become better at sticking to habits in a simple and easy way. This book starts off with a quick introduction to habits themselves and specifically what is an ‘Atomic Habit’. The author then moves on to lay the foundations of habit formation - the ‘cue, craving, respose, reward’ cycle. These phases of the habit formation and retention should be familiar to you if you’ve read ‘The Power of Habit’ by Charles Duhigg. But, instead of reiterating the same concepts, James Clear takes on a journey of putting these phases into a very practical framework to master any habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of this book is that it not only talks about forming a new habit, but also provides effective approaches to get rid of old habits. If reducing the TV time is your priority, this book has you covered. And it does so by not giving lengthy lectures on self-control, but by practical tips which will definitely work for you. For each of the above habit phase mentioned earlier, there’s a chapter on habit formation and there’s one on habit reduction. At the end of each section, you will find a handy one-liner summaries of each of the chapters covered so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atomic Habits builds upon the foundations laid by some of the most famour books on human behaviour - ‘The Power of Habit’, ‘Thinking Fast and Slow’, ‘Outliers’, ‘Blink’, ‘Flow’ and others. If you’ve read the above books, some of the contents of Atomic Habits will remind the deeper concepts in each of these books; which I believe provides a good segue into picking up your next book to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my favorite lines from the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habits are the compound interest of self-improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Success is the product of daily habits - not once-in-a-lifetime transformations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The biggest barrier to positive change at any level - individual, team, society - is identity conflict.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most practical way to change &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; you are is to change &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; you do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identity change is the North star of habit change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Environment is the invisible hand that shapes human behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The people with the best self-control are typically the ones who need to use it the least.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can break a habit, but you’re unlikely to forget it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Desire is the engine that drives behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nothing sustains motivation better than belonging to the tribe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Running against the grain of your culture requires extra effort.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once we fit in, we start looking for ways to stand out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Desire is the difference between where you are now and where you want to be in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habits are easier to build if they fit into the flow of your life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is rewarded is repeated, what is punished is avoided.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incentives can start a habit. Identity sustains a habit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Missing once is an accident. Missing twice is the start of a new habit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pain is an effective teacher.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionals stick to the schedule, amateurs let life get in the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>First Post</title>
   <link href="https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2020/10/04/first-post/"/>
   <updated>2020-10-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>https://vjyrakesh.github.io/blog/2020/10/04/first-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello again! This is my first post in the newly created blog of my personal website. Going forward, this will be the home to all my blog posts hereafter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy reading! Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
